[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
for software engineering radio this is
robert blumen today i have with me sam
boyer sam is a principal software
engineer at grafana labs contributes to
open source projects especially in the
go community and he's the author of the
article so you want to write a package
manager which will be the subject of our
conversation today sam welcome to
software engineering radio
thank you for having me i'm delighted to
be here is there anything else you'd
like listeners to know about your
background
i can do the quick things i have been
i'm a self-taught engineer i started in
the
industry about 12 years ago i've been
working in open source for a long
long time and it was in large part my
interest in the way the communities work
that drove me to
my interest in package management in the
first place great before we talk about
package management what is a package
so this is this is a totally natural
place to start and it is
a surprisingly
subtle question so
most people most the time
think of i think the
the packages they work with in terms of
the actual
systems they're in right you know if
you're writing
javascript or typescript or whatever
you're going to think of npm packages
and package.json and like the contents
of that you might also think of system
packages or system package managers for
your old apps or your rpms or more
modern like kubernetes things
but if you actually want to like give a
sufficiently general definition of what
a package is it's
kind of frustratingly useless like the
best one i can give is that a package is
a collection of stuff with a name and
some kind of logical boundary that
separates the stuff that it contains
from other packages of the same kind at
their stuff within some larger context
and that is a it's it's like i said
frustratingly abstract like stuff can be
source code or compiled code or
configuration files or a bunch of cat
gifs like what's
the contents of the package and what it
means to be a valid package is a
function of the ecosystem that the
package is from
it's an npm package it should have
certain properties it should have a
package json a rust package should have
a cargo tunnel and i think a non-zero
number of rs
files this is one of the weird
subtleties of package management though
it starts right at the beginning is it's
hard to actually pin a really precise
definition on what constitutes a package
might help people to understand if you
could pick one language and talk about
one or more packages in that language to
illustrate it
okay offhand oh man oh would i pick
so in
go
we could talk about
go where the the thing that we think of
as packages elsewhere are referred to as
modules we could talk about like the go
kit package sure popular micro services
framework
and so
that is a there's a git repository that
the actual process of developing the
code is done in but what we would think
of as a package itself is
a git tag that is attached to a
particular commit to make a release
that refers to then the snapshot of all
the files in the git repository and
the identifying features of that
go package would be all the go files
themselves and then the metadata files
that communicate information at the
package level the go.mod file to go.some
file in the case of
go okay so packages so it's a bunch of
code that i might want to use in my
program so i don't have to go to the
trouble of writing it all
myself and then there's some metadata
in if it's too hard to answer this in
general talk about some things you might
find in the metadata you could pick a
particular language yeah well i mean the
the most important things that you're
going to find in metadata you're always
going to find a name and you may or may
not find a version
sometimes that is considered to be
something that is held inside of the
package but it always has to be
something that's also like outside of
the package so that other things can
refer to
it but that's sort of your your your
two-point coordinate system in in the
universe of of packages is you need to
have a name and then a particular
version of that name right good yeah i
don't only want to use a go kit
package i want you to know that i want
2.1
right and they might release 2.2 2.3 but
i'm not ready to upgrade to 2.3 so i
want to stay on 2.1 something like that
yeah yeah those are the those are the
two absolute essentials the other major
thing that
you
will typically see in these metadata
files is you'll see a list of
dependencies list of other packages
required by that package and possibly
also some construction about the version
that's supposed to be
used with those the answer to this is
going to be in very broad ranges
if i'm if i'm building a a product let's
say it's a commercial product that is
running for business somewhere
and so i'm going to build a
server
how many packages
might if we look at the packages and
their dependencies and we have to go all
the way down to the bottom we talking
tens hundreds thousands how many
packages does a typical modern software
application need
so it really depends on the ecosystem
you're going to see a lot more in
the
npm ecosystem than you would in
the call ecosystem or the rust ecosystem
for example i don't have like
i'm not sure that i would be able to
meaningfully construct like an average
number if only because
you can't like even if i had access to
all the if i had access to all the
private software written everywhere in
the world then i could construct like an
average number but there's a selection
bias involved with polling only the open
source available ones so i think the
best i can say is yeah you might see
thousands in in javascript land and you
might see tens to hundreds in like a go
or a or a rust and i don't i think most
of the other
javascript is really the one that is
like an order of magnitude more than
most npm yeah this means
that if i am
shipping software that most of what i'm
shipping
is stuff written by other people my
contribution is only a tiny amount
you get into this a little bit in your
article when you talk about yeah maybe
we want to talk about like what a
package manager does first that actually
might be a better way to
let's move on to our main topic which is
we need some kind of a tool
i think that's motivated by if there's
thousands of these things it goes beyond
human comprehension to keep track of all
the packages
what problem does a package manager
solve
so i mean the
obvious thing that it does right is it
like downloads a bunch of stuff from
the internet and
puts it in places on
on disk so that you can run programs so
in a sense it's an automation
tool but i think that as with a lot of
automation
the value is not so much
certainly there's value in keeping from
having you to do rote tasks over and
over again but it's in the uniformity of
the way that a system is created on the
other side of like running a package
manager command all of the same packages
all the same versions it's part of a
like a reproducible build concept that
when you have a tool that
grabs everything in a uniform way and
lays it out in a uniform way it removes
the goal is usually to remove
unnecessary choice from the operator in
terms of how all these these
dependencies are arranged
okay so it's going to ensure that you
have reasonable versions of all the
packages that you need so you can do a
build is that a fair statement
yeah the and actually the word the word
reasonable is incredibly important here
because version selection is the core of
of all of this like which versions of
the packages do you actually want to use
and
i my
stance is that we should actually think
about
the job of a package manager as at least
by default its job is to pick the
correct version which itself is a term
that we need to unpack
but it sets us in the right frame of
mind that the the real job of package
managers
is to
be a system that
has an opinion about what it means for
the like artifact it creates on the
other side the composition of your code
and all your dependency code
to be correct and to enforce that and to
tell you when it can't meet that
yeah
okay we're going to come back to the
dependency
versioning issue and discuss that in
depth in a bit
could you toss out the names of some
popular languages and frameworks and the
package managers
that go along with them
sure we've got there's
node and npm or yarn and then there's
rust and cargo and
go and go modules is the way you should
probably refer to it
we're talking about commonalities to
something that exists in nearly all
different software is the package
manager
usually
issued or built by the same
team that built the language itself and
it comes as a part of a toolkit
if i download
python i would get the python package
manager or does there tend to be
competition among package managers even
within the same language community where
different developers have a different
idea of how
package management should be done for
language a and so you would have a range
of choices
even within language a
yeah nowadays
i think it's pretty well accepted
that
you really can't ship a language without
shipping a package manager at least not
if you want any kind of community to
exist
but that's not always been the case
certainly so there is a shift in this
over time older languages
you will there's more separation between
like the language tooling and the
package manager newer ones tend to build
a writer
would the package manager be written in
the same language
as the primary language
yeah almost always the main limit here
is that
you
absolutely have to have your package
manager be ex executable
wherever your language is executable and
as nice as it might be if like
we could write the
mother algorithm for all package
management in like one language
you end up in a really awkward situation
as a language designer if you're having
to juggle between your compiler or
whatever and like what platforms it can
run on and then your package manager not
being aligned
for example python itself is built in c
but
i wouldn't necessarily want to have to
have a c compiler
just to build a python package manager
it should be written in python okay now
take a python it's a language i'm
familiar with there are many packages
which are built in to python i don't
need to manage them because when i get
python i get a bunch of
common packages is it a requirement that
the package manager only depend on
built-ins so that we don't have to
package manage
while we're bootstrapping the package
manager
i mean it i think that's
mostly a question of
the more has to do with
the previous question right like is the
package manager a part of the tool chain
that's distributed with the language if
it is well probably yes we're not going
to depend on anything external if it's
not then do you have more degrees of
freedom
there okay package manager you mentioned
that it goes out to
the interwebs and finds things
where does it go
to find the packages
yeah
so there's a few there's a few
approaches most package managers rely on
some kind of central repository i would
say you can really say there's there's
four models you can have
the model where there is only one
central repository you can have the
model where there's like a search
algorithm that picks between multiple
repositories that can be specified you
can try to go fully distributed and use
like a like i've seen a couple of
blockchain related package managers that
want to like store the packages on the
blockchain so your addresses are not
going to a server they're instead going
to this this distributed address
resolution system
not finding good words there and then
you can go for something more
strictly like url shape like the actual
names of your packages are
urls effectively and so you're relying
on dns to give meaning to names
at least the highest level instead of a
like a central service so if it's
built into the package manager there's a
one
repository everything's there it goes
there we could
put the name of the repository in the
code
if there are several or i want it to be
configurable would there be a setup step
or i usually some command like add
remote repository followed by a url
yeah if if that's the that's the model
that's been chosen by the the creators
of the package manager the the scope of
this ends up being really important
right like
for a system package manager you might
configure at a system level
you know in your etsy directory some
additional repositories that get used
right that way all users share them one
of the main issues is that since we're
ultimately talking about name resolution
here
is
in order to have
multiple repositories you have to have a
way
of distributing
the names of all of the name resolution
services effectively to
any client that's going to end up trying
to resolve all those packages because
otherwise you don't have the same
uniformity across all of your users that
is so important within an enterprise
there could be security reasons or
availability reasons why you might not
want to pull everything from a remote
repository or perhaps the amount of
bandwidth going over the network suppose
we want either to run our own repository
or have caches or mirrors on a
internal network
is that a common use case and do all of
these package managers support that it's
a range it's certainly common there's
any number of reasons whether it is
performance security i guess those are
the two major broad categories of
reasons that that jump to mine right
away actually i supposed to be
performance security and then also
correctness in the sense of ensuring
uniform name resolution again would be
the major reasons that people want some
kind of intermediary to
to not just have things touching
the interwebs the manner in which these
are supported
varies i'm i'm not aware of any
like general framework for being able to
talk about it mostly because the way
that you would inject an intermediary is
largely a function of
how your name resolution works in the
first place and so it's dependent upon
something that varies in the first place
across packet managers
how does the package get
pushed up into the repository
this is uh it's so it's very clear that
package managers are responsible for the
read step they have varying degrees of
responsibility for the right
path
it's more common when you have a
repository that you that you maintain
yourself that is specific to your
ecosystem of packages that the
tool will bundle in the right path
but this also gets into
like the nature of what your
what your package actually contains
right i mean it's you're making a
release so you generally want to like
hook this kind of thing into a ci
workflow something that gives you
assurances that the thing you're about
to release is correct with respect to
whatever rules you've devised for your
package
and yeah then then you have to figure
out how how to map the
i think what i'm trying to say is like
with respect to
the tooling the job of the people
writing the package manager is
to probably be as
as non-invasive as possible into
people's workflows because people are
going to put a lot of different things
together
when it comes to being sure that they're
actually ready to make a release and
trying to bake too much of that
into
into like what you would write in the in
a standard tool for package management
ends up
hindering because you're cutting off
certain workflows that will be important
to people so if i have a compiled
language maybe my source code is in git
hub i've decided this code it's passed
all the validations we're ready to
release
2.4
there would be some workflow i would go
through which might involve compiling
and creating libs or jars or whatever
the
archival format is and then pushing
those up into
an account that i have for our project
on the repository server
is that what the workflow looks like
yeah more or less yeah perhaps it's
something that i mean especially
nowadays you know i would expect that
this kind of thing is
something you would create an automation
for which is very important i mean again
the
the goal with packages in general
is this uniformity of the package object
and removing as much
a necessary source of user error in the
process of both creating and consuming
these things is essential to
reliability so
yeah
automate that but in general yeah what
you described is
is the way that one should imagine using
it do the package manager support an api
that looks like give me all the versions
you know about
of this package by name
usually yes it's almost impossible to
write a version selection algorithm
without having knowledge of the
universal versions
are there
validations like
code signing to ensure that what you get
is the trusted package that you asked
for
yeah this is i mean the tricky thing
here is since we're we're down at the
level of like
giving meaning to names
you can easily get to the canonicality
issues when it comes to like
verifying the original upstream source
you know if i if
if i have a if i have a repository in
some configuration file that i have
added then that thing needs to be the
thing that i check against for the
validity of the package name that i'm
asking it to resolve but if someone can
attack like
the config file that i have about which
repository that i talk to then how do i
know that my verification is correct
this the whole feel of you know software
supply chain security is invested in in
trying to
formalize a lot of the answers to this
so that we at least don't have a lot of
unforced errors in in this area but yes
certainly that can be a part of of the
process and can be considered an aspect
of what
constitutes the correctness of a package
that is a great topic i would like for
us to do an entire hour or i mean
software engineering radio to do entire
hour on supply chain security at some
point
but to continue with it our discussion
what does the developer workflow look
like
when using a package manager and if
there isn't a general
case answer then it's pick one language
that you can talk about
what are the
developer runs
i mean there are a pretty general set of
of commands right like and they are
essentially they're they're cruddish
it's i want to add a package i want to
change the version of the package i want
to remove a package
add a package
sorry here we're talking like this is
the developer working on a project
talking about the dependencies for the
project that they're in correct yeah uh
yeah
so yeah let's drill down into that so so
add packages i've decided i need to do
some feature in my
program and there's a package for it i
know the name i know the package i want
so i'm going to add a package do i have
a
config file
that tells the package manager here are
all the packages i want i go and edit
that config file and then i run a
command like
sync or add
can be it varies the
in general the two interfaces to package
managers are a command line interface
and then a file because you certainly
have to record state in order to be able
to do anything with with a package
manager you have to record dependencies
it's typically far more convenient to
offer people a command line interface
to to do most of these things
more scriptable etc because then the
other thing that you can do which is
especially important for for automation
purposes is
if you're able to have
the tool
take its action and then update the
written file this is usually the most
preferable flow
not sure i follow what you mean by that
do you mean if i add a package to the
code
that the package manager might detect
this package is missing i need to add it
to the package list
yeah that if i if i say you know add
dependency foo
on my in my terminal i do
package add foo then
when
the command completes if the command
completes successfully
i should be able to expect that
that package is present and available
on my file system or whatever it means
for the package to be available
such that when i go to like execute the
program the linker the loader whatever
it is is able to get at the contents of
the package so i can expect that that
requirement is satisfied and also that
a record of the require a record that
the requirement of the package exists
is written into this thing we usually
call a manifest file i realize i don't
like this package i'm going to remove it
from the code
what does the remove workflow look like
so the i mean the main thing that's
really tricky here right is that
usually
the question is what the relationship is
between the metadata file
and the actual code base like if you
have import statements that continue to
reference a that continue to reference a
package which you are trying to remove i
mean i'm not really sure why you're
trying to do that there there are
reasons to do it but there isn't like a
general case for it so what we're really
talking about is a synchronization
relationship between the dependencies as
expressed in the code and the
dependencies as expressed in the package
level metadata
so
are you referring to the case where like
usually what this entails is
the developer needs to go in and excise
any references to the package from their
code and the final step is just like
remove it from the metadata function yes
okay yeah now i think it would be a good
time to start going
into dependencies
you talked about this a little earlier
where
i like this package it does something
useful
i'm going to add it to my package
manager
this package
because it's software
it relies on
other packages which are its
dependencies so you have recursive
process
so before i ask you some more questions
anything
you'd like to say generally about
dependencies and then we'll get into
some more detailed discussion sure i
mean so the the graph of connections
between
software packages and and the packages
that they depend on
and certain key rules about this graph
which include well certain key rules
about that graph are some of the most
important fundamental properties of any
package
ecosystem and i'm sure the next
questions you have will drive us right
at those clearly we don't want
circular dependencies but cycle is a
property of the entire graph
how does a developer of a package ensure
that they're not depending on something
that is
in the wrong layer and would create
potentially create a cycle in general
they can't i mean because as you noted
it's a it's a property of the graph
right certainly i'm not sure that
there's a general answer to cycles most
package managers do allow
cycles of some kind at least
primarily because it's mostly like not
up to an individual developer to to
resolve that like it's no it's a little
kind of the definition of a cycle right
like it's no one person's fault if
there's well at least there's three oh
no it's not one person's fault there's a
cycle because the arrows go in a circle
whether or not you can
construct a sane logical system on the
other side of there being dependency
cycles tends to be the challenge and the
reason why you wouldn't allow
cyclic dependencies at the
package level
yeah okay now i we've established if i
want a package i have to specify
the version i want
the package itself
is going to specify
versions or maybe a range of versions of
its dependencies how do versions and
dependencies interact
so yeah this is the most one of the most
important properties
for any ecosystem i think i'll talk
first about about like
ranges versus sorry first i'll talk
about what yehuda katz likes to call the
uh the highlander rule and then i'll
talk about uh version ranges so
every
package ecosystem
needs to make a decision about whether
given that you know given a and b and
they both depend on c
every package ecosystem
or rather the the thing consuming the
package ecosystem needs to decide
whether
there are two instances of c or one
one for a one for b or one that they
both have to share
and the semantics of that are
complicated they have to do with what
actual kind of artifact you're trying to
create on the other side of putting a b
and c
together it tends to be
that
compiled languages or at least
statically type statically type checked
languages
have a lot of difficulty allowing that
duplication
it's necessary to
come to a compromise on the version so
that there can be exactly one instance
of c so that names have proper meaning
so that you can
let types flow through the program and
not have
your type checker blow up dynamic
languages can get away without it
and sure enough npm until recently at
least until npm 7 basically name spaced
everything and most other languages
don't they
follow the rule there has to there could
be only one this is the source of the
highlander reference there can be only
one seed okay let me give an example if
i'm bringing in different packages and
all of those packages use logging
it might happen that package a
says i want 1.4 of the logging package
and package b says
no i want 1.5 of logging you're saying
there are two solutions one is great we
have a uses 1.4 and b is 1.5 we have two
versions of logging
now that might not work because
this could depend on the language
runtime that
logging is some kind of a unique name in
the language you can't
namespace it so now you have to agree
or just because of the nature of what
logging is maybe
the log aggregator you use you can only
have one of them
those are the different
options you're talking about correct
yeah those yeah so the the if so if okay
if you have uh let's imagine that we
have a
a depends on b and a depends on c b and
c both depend on logging
the question is
from from a type checking perspective is
it possible that any of the logging
types
flow back through
back up into a and need to be the same
type because they actually rejoin an a
and the type checker needs to approve
that all these types are valid if you're
in a language where you do have a type
checker and we have to be sure of that
in order to compile then it's generally
not feasible to
have multiple instances of c because
they have different names they've been
namespaced somehow and the type checker
is going to blow up in a dynamic
language
you can get by without it the other
thing is what you're talking about where
essentially if c relies usually it's a
global state question if c relies on
some kind of well global state or
external resources question
but
it's effectively the same thing like
if the the conventional thing gets
talked about here is more like a
database connection if c has a database
connection embedded in it somehow you
don't necessarily want to have two
copies of it because you don't want two
copies of a connection to your database
in some languages there's a concept of
global variable the language would not
allow you to have two global variables
that are different but have the same
name so in that case you have to agree
on they're say an object called logging
and it's a global variable in some cases
that can only be one
yep okay now
what am i going to see if i run a
package
add or sync command
if it detects an issue of this type
what am i going to see in the output
so it it this this is where it gets very
interesting in
the the first things you want to talk
about is a
a language which does not follow the
highlander rule right you can you can
duplicate vlogging yeah i mean in that
case like we don't have a problem right
you what you're going to see is success
great you know we picked this version
for this version of logging for a in
this version of logging for b
in a language where you do have to solve
the problem you have a few different
there are a few different options and
they really depend on the way that the
version selection algorithm for that
package manager works
so
there are
some package managers which
use a version selection algorithm that
essentially can't fail
perhaps even when it should
so
there are advantages to this approach
mostly
algorithmically it's faster and it's the
behavior tends to be more predictable
so even though you get you know
even though you can plausibly get a an
outcome which like won't actually
compile you
you at least don't have odd failures
because the problem is the failures get
really complicated too so if you
have a version selection algorithm which
sees the problem and tries to do
something
about it we're now talking about the
search problem effectively can we find
versions of b and c
which can agree
on
a version of logging
and
then we get into
the question of
what agreement means but the output that
you may see in that case it'll vary
widely like
it varies depending on whether or not it
was possible to find a version of
logging that b and c agree on because if
it was then the package manager probably
won't tell you there's a problem it'll
just say i picked this version because
it appears to satisfy constraints
if it did fail to find a version
the output can be potentially very
complicated because there it may have
gone
in order to exhaust the possibility
space of all the different versions of b
and c it may have a whole lot to tell
you about all the things that didn't
work
so there there's a there's a range of
output you may see
an example we gave a few minutes ago we
were talking about package b1's logging
1.4 in package c1 slogging 1.5
you could imagine package pieces i am
comfortable with 1.4 or greater up to
2.0 and package c says i want 1.7 or
greater up to 3.0 there is clearly an
intersect
of things they could both agree on but
there could be more than one right
answer
how does a package manager
choose you could have a range of
acceptable versions how does it choose
so this is
i mean that is effectively that question
reduces to how does a
how does a stat solver work you you have
a range of possible versions and i mean
in general the the simplest way to think
about it is
latest version acceptable from all
parties is the one that you should
get but that is actually a deeply
insufficient answer itself because just
because you're running version selection
doesn't actually mean that you want to
update like if
b requires
logging 1.5 and c requires logging 1.4
and you're a and you're pulling in b and
c both at the first time well if there's
a version of c that is 1.6
does that mean you should get that
version of c that's 1.6 because that's
not the version that either b or c asked
for in the first place
there's a range of considerations here
that are that are not easy to
to resolve in a straightforward way the
thing though that i think is important
to point to
is that even if
well sorry not even if it's easy to look
at these numbers and almost be like oh
this is fine i get to write an algorithm
that like
solves constraints but the reality is
that those constraints that are written
down are almost
like almost certainly wrong
almost anything that you write down at
least if you are asking of your
version range version constraint system
if you are asking the user to make a
precise statement about which versions
of its dependencies the software
actually works with for a range of
reasons
that is almost never going to actually
be
correct
so this is why well people talk about
dependency hell right the problem where
you're trying to essentially negotiate
between b and c with logging right you
know your a there's b and c they depend
on logging they disagree
which version like works i think
actually it's more interesting to talk
about dependency limbo and dependency
health
because i think we spend a lot of time
in dependency limbo where
we're confused about the output from our
package manager and we are unsure
as to whether there does exist or not
a version of logging that will satisfy
vnc
then there's two branches of that
question there is is there a version of
logging that will satisfy b and c
according to what they've written down
and then is there a version of logging
that will satisfy b and c according to
reality like will my code actually
compile and be correct whether or not
the things that b and c wrote down about
logging actually are satisfied
so dependency hell i would say is when
there's a real problem and well compiled
and your code's incorrect and dependency
limbo is when you're just not sure
let's delve a bit more into dependency
health
would this be where
i
run the sync it says you get two
conflicting versions of
logging
one of your packages needs
1.4 or less and one of them needs 1.5 or
greater so i say okay i'm going to
upgrade some things to get on a higher
version of logging
and that should resolve that and then it
breaks something else
sure i think there's many circles in
dependency held and the problem is that
because ultimately we're we're at this
10 000 foot view of the actual
behavior of our software and we're
trying to make really coarse-grained
choices to arrange things in our
dependency tree just in order to get
things to work yes certainly i change in
order to satisfy that in order to deal
with b and c's issue with logging i
update other things and then things
break over there like it ends up being a
problem where you can suck in the
entirety of your application just trying
to fix one
problem and it's it's difficult to tell
which way is even up
could imagine this happening
we're talking about logging which is
something pretty concrete i usually know
which logging system i want to use
but it could also be that i'm pulling in
some very high level packages to do some
something like machine learning and
seven levels deep
they
give me the name of something that's
live g r p n f
zero here i don't even know what that
does
i never asked for it
i don't want it i don't know what the
risks are if i
say just go ahead and use this anyway
and i wouldn't really know how to
resolve it what do i do sam
that you you you mourn the dependency
hell is real i mean this this is this is
why again i kind of like the limbo thing
more is because
what is hellish about the experience so
often is our uncertainty about what is
okay to do we are often solving problems
that are not our own in some deeply
nested set of packages why did they make
these decisions are these constraints
real can i violate them and still have
things be correct how can i be sure that
things are correct on the other side of
violating them how can i be sure they're
correct even if i haven't violated them
like it's this this series of questions
that is like usually these systems work
well enough
that certainly we all get by with them
but there is this there's this cliff and
much of it involves just the the gray
uncertainty about how to fix problems
when they arise and whether problems
exist in the first place
is there typically a command or setting
where i can and and perhaps what you
mean by dependency in limbo i can make
the call that this package says it needs
one dot
or a high or one to four or less but i
am pretty sure it's gonna work with 1.5
they developer did not upgrade is a bit
too strict so i'm going to say
pax measures says you have these two
conflicting versions on the 41.5 i can
say
go with 1.5 i'll take the consequences
usually yes these are referred to
typically the the general term that's
used to refer to these is some kind of
override right like i from the root of
the package graph want to supersede
something down
i have to fix a problem so i'm going to
supersede something that one of my
dependencies has
said the classic problem with overrides
though is that
it is
it's really only a power that can be
given to the root package in the graph
it's not
that there's no way to
the reason we have these issues in the
first place is because you know b issues
a constraint on on on logging and see
issues of constraint on logging and like
we error out if we can't find anything
where their constraints can be made to
agree right the point of an override is
well
this has higher priority than everything
else but as soon as you're down in the
depth like if b had an override in c
hadn't over it wouldn't matter because
now we can't pick one which you know
supersedes so what this creates is like
if you end up having to rely on an
override switch as the author of a
package i refer to this as contagion
failure because if you have to write
down an override then anybody who
depends on you has to copy that override
they have to hoist it into their own
metadata in order to get the graph to
resolve in the same way and it's usually
invisible to
whoever's depending on you
that they need to do so so it's this
just like spread of overrides that that
goes through the package graph and the
deeper it gets the worse it gets sounds
very fragile if
then you upgrade something it probably
breaks all the overrides you did
plausible in fact yeah yeah depending on
how overrides or phrase it's certainly
phrased it certainly can like if you
were saying use version
one seven instead of version one eight
of of logging effectively but then like
the version of logging that was being
used changed now you're not replacing
one seven anymore because one seven
wasn't the version that was there in the
first place and you heard your like
override statements and effective how do
you even know that that happened it's
yeah the problem metastasizes i think it
now would be good time to delve a bit
into the internals of package manager
we've talked about
some of the components there's the
project code that has import statements
some kind of a manifest file
so at least two more components next one
would be a lock file
please talk about that sure so i mean a
lock file is really the result of a
version selection computation i went
through and the idea is i want to record
the exact set of dependencies at a given
moment in
time transitively so you have the entire
graph written out in a file these are
the these are all the dependencies these
are the versions it is not
strictly necessary depending on the
package manager to have a lock file
because it depends on the algorithm if
you have a stable algorithm then you
don't necessarily need to have a lock
file this is why go modules doesn't have
log file because the algorithm is stable
stable is an imprecise word because the
algorithm never
picks the latest version
it means that given a set of
specific versioned inputs
you can walk all the way down through
the graph and and know that you'll
always get the same set of versions
modulo certain details but
version selection algorithms which do
like default to latest
need to have a lock file because
otherwise there's no way to have
reproducible builds at all but
ultimately the goal of the lock file is
this reproducible build properly
property if you had something which
could pick latest then latest could
change because if that package developer
is pushed and update
yeah and so okay so you don't have a
reproducible build now because it
depends on something external
right this is often referred to as like
people often refer to
this sort of ambigu ambiguously actually
but as version pinning like i want to
use
exactly a version the ambiguity tends to
be
whether
you've written down whether it's pinned
because it's the version that you have
written down in the lock file or it's
pinned because it's the version you've
written on the manifest file the meaning
of having it in the log file tends to be
this is what i'm using right now and we
want it to be reproducible but it could
change whereas a manifest file says i
will use this version and only this
exact version it's a constraint
statement right depending on the
language if i have the lock file then
would the build system typically support
the ability to do
a build and here's the lock file don't
run the package dependency algorithm
again
we're starting in midstream because
we've already run it
that's really it's a good way to think
about the log file is like i said it's
the result of a version selection
computation so the presence of the lock
file is usually used as an indication
that use the versions that are here we
don't need to rerun version selection
we've done it and this is the version
that we committed to so you know
continue forward in your in your build
system i do think there are interesting
possible universes where
we could do a lot more like version
selection
further down in our
pipelines in our ci pipelines our
delivery pipelines but it it requires
some some new
algorithm and and it's some new thinking
about how we about how we encode this
information what would be the advantage
of doing that so it would be
that
instead of having to
like you could imagine the context of
perhaps a b testing or
well
if you had the ability to
change
the set of dependencies being used
for a given piece of software perhaps
not on the fly but that you could change
it somewhere later in your in your build
pipeline instead of having to like have
multiple build pipelines where you
expressly commit a particular version to
be tested and now you're like back in
get land trying to think about this way
this maze of branches that you've
created you can express
a combinatorial set of build variations
that you might want to test that are
like a a logical consequence of
like a matrix of versions or matrix of
constraints that you pass to the
algorithm and have some knowledge of of
which versions will actually be
tested that's one thing anyway this is a
it's a relatively distant concept so i'm
not sure how it would end up being used
could there be an example of this where
there's some library that's
very low level
that has tremendous throughput like
networking
and i want to see if i bump a version if
i either have a performance regression
or performance improvement
and so yeah i i could do that by
changing the version in
the manifest or the lock file and
putting it on a branch and building that
branch but
yep you're saying yeah i think
yeah that you could basically you could
design you can imagine designing sort of
you can imagine designing checks
which want to continuously
check against some
some range of of
versions for some library some
particular property yeah like the
performance of some some networking
throughput library the advantage of of
this
it's it's hard to talk about because
there's a few this this is something
that i'm working on but
it's hard to talk about because there's
a few concepts that you need to have
kind of before you can get to the value
of it and like explaining the the
concepts that get there is is kind of
out of scope
the simple way of saying it is that you
need a language that you can use to
express
which versions are acceptable to select
which are which is then sort of usable
on the other side to talk about which
versions have been selected relative to
what is like committed to in in a log
file and that can then be used to like
parameterize your concept of what your
build actually looks like but that's i
think it's probably the most
comprehensible
way to say it and i don't think it's
very comprehensible the last component
would be the dependencies themselves
where does the
dependency manager put them after it
grabs them off the internet
yeah so i mean again of course this this
varies significantly from package from
package manager to package manager and
the question there is really tied
to
the behavior of
the
so given given that packages are tied to
a particular ecosystem and there is an
intent of using packages in a particular
way whether it's an interpreter or a
compiler or
as an intermediate stage like a to a
larger um to something larger
there has there is some program that is
going to
tie together all these dependencies and
it has to know how to locate them so
this is really sort of a how do i locate
things problem
the like the
the og package manager is really
i mean we think about system package
managers those are actually c package
managers because we didn't really make
this the distinction between all of all
of the code in our live directory which
was going to be used by c and i am
a package config which would you know
actually go and like locate packages for
you
on disk for most of the languages though
this is a more
self-contained problem and
the way that packages get arranged is
mostly a question of sort of look up
convenience for the language the main
thing to say about it is kind of an and
a note that like what gets weird about
package lookups is this is where you
tend to want to do something like
aliasing or
some sort of of override methods and
some of it is important but they're
if you give too much flexibility to the
user to be able to just sort of rename
packages all over the place they will
consistently people will will use it for
things that end up getting them getting
their program into just an
incomprehensible state because we're
effectively overwriting names upon
overwriting names or messing with things
with where they are on the file system
in general where the packages
live should be the most boring question
that you can possibly ask of a package
manager it should be rote and simple and
dumb because doing anything else makes
things really confusing
i was going to ask you this question
about the lock file
which i forgot so i'm going to combine
this with the question about dependency
should the lock file be committed to
your
yes that's cm and what about the
dependencies when they're downloaded
should those be committed
i'm agnostic
the there there are reasons to do it
you know it's it's easy to point to
things like left pad which is god
a decade old no i don't even know how
old it is you know where where people
have pulled
packages from from public repositories
and you're trying to like guard against
that
sure
but
most of the strategies for trying to
defend yourself against like
the the world changing
tend to
have a limited shelf life i'm not saying
that they're wrong and everybody has a
different way of sort of thinking about
the
the risk profile here in general i tend
not to
commit my dependencies but there is i
view it as mostly like a sort of risk
assessment argument that that people
reasonable people can disagree on
language like go or the c
languages the end of the build systems
it produces a binary which
may incorporate all of the libraries
to the point where you don't need them i
understand there are some things have
dynamically loaded libraries compared to
ruby or python where you need the
packages because it's
interpreting them at runtime and so that
would be a stronger case why you should
possibly check them in because you can't
deploy
without them i mean you know the
question there is whether
you want
failure to happen at deployment or like
failure to happen with your developers
failure's still happening
i'm not sure how meaningfully different
those things are and that may depend on
your context
so we have a bit of time left you had a
discussion in your article and if you
can
condense this in the remaining time the
steps that happen we've we've talked
about the components broadly what does
the thing do what are the steps that
happen when the package manager runs
referencing the
manifest lock file dependencies and
other state
the steps so when it runs referring to
our
get or add remove or or change
which one
let's start with let's do add that's
probably what we have time for
sure yeah so most really what's
happening here is we're trying to
reconcile a few different states right
we are
depending on the language
possibly trying to
scan over source code like you can do
this in go scan over the source code to
look at import statements and try to
ensure that all of those are satisfied
that's that's something you may be doing
and you may be doing that independent of
which command you're running but with an
ad command the basic validation that you
have to do in the command initially is
like well is there actually a thing to
add here like if you try to add food and
food's already in your manifest then
what are we doing it doesn't make any
sense but once we've established that
like it's a sort of valid request then
you
have to resolve the name how do i know
what foo is
and that's going to depend on the
choices we were talking about earlier
for the package manager about what thing
you use to resolve names
and
if
if the thing resolves you're going to
fetch it down
and at that point you have to
then kick off
well what you really have to do at that
point is you have to kick off version
selection because there's there's no way
to
there's the thing about version
selection because it's all a graph you
have no way of knowing a priori which
packages might depend on which other
packages in order to add a you have to
reconsider the entire graph so you run
through a version selection process to
basically pick a new version for all of
your dependencies
and
including including a with that then you
assuming that that was successful you
get a return out and that ends up
getting piped back to the user ideally
that manifest file gets updated and the
log file gets updated as well
and you get a successful return to the
user i think that's a good place to stop
sam we've covered a lot of ground here i
hope those centers have a better
understanding of this somewhat murky
area than they did an hour ago
before we
wrap up is there any place listeners
could find or follow you that you'd like
to point them at i'm on twitter at sd
boyer
any open resources nowadays but yeah
any open source projects
so i have a uh
i have a new thing that i'm working on
which is not unrelated to
package management and the repository is
well in a week it it should be much more
consumable but i'm calling it scumada
it's written in the new language queue
it's a system for writing schema
but it's a system for writing schema
that
lets you evolve the schema over time
including across breaking changes and
encapsulate all the logic for writing
the schema
and the dealing with breaking changes
into one place and that's it github
slash grafana slash schumada and i
assume that we can put
well should i spell it out how should i
put it i'll get it from your own put
i'll put it in the show notes cool i
think that's probably the most
interesting thing it's like i said not
unrelated to package management but has
much more to do with the way that you
the way you deal with breakage which is
certainly a major topic in pakistan
sam boyer thank you very much for
speaking to software engineering radio
thank you it's been great
this has been robert blumen thank you
for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
[Music]